Boker tov בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today today's
daf דף daf is yud aleph י"א, yud aleph, eleven, and we
pick up at the bottom of yud amud bet י' עמוד ב'
yud amud bet
and the Gemara גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay,
we are at Sukkah al gabi hasukkah סוכה על גבי הסוכה. Sukkah
al gabi hasukkah. We'll read that. So it's about ten lines from
the bottom, line starts with the word veharei והרי veharei and the
issue here is the following. The Mishnah משנה Mishnah said that if
somebody is in a sleep under a canopy in a Sukkah סוכה,
Sukkah, they don't fulfill their obligation. If however they sleep under a
tepee shaped canopy with two poles at the end rather than four
and like a bar going horizontally,
then it's okay because then it doesn't create a separate roof. If
it's not a tefach טפח tefach on the top, it's not a
separate roof. That seems reasonable enough. Then came along a lenient reading
of
of Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel רב יהודה אמר שמואל Rav Yehuda amar
Shmuel that said that even if it is a roof
like a normal roof, it's only a problem if it's ten tefachim
טפחים tefachim high. Only then is it like you're in a separate
zone, in a separate tent, but if it's a lower roof, if
it's a lower canopy, it's not a problem. So you needed two
criteria, it had to have a roof for you to be in
this tent in the Sukkah סוכה Sukkah and for it to be
ten tefachim טפחים tefachim high. But the Gemara גמרא Gemara had a
baraita ברייתא baraita that seemed to say either criteria was a problem,
not both. Actually let's start again from asking from the baraita ברייתא
baraita and we'll pick it up from there. So it says like
this, it says tash ma תא שמע. tash ma. Do people see
where I am? Yeah about twenty lines from the bottom, the line
starts with the word migavo'a asara מגבוה עשרה. migavo'a asara. Okay, so
the Gemara גמרא Gemara says tash ma תא שמע tash ma o
shepireis al gabi kinofot psula או שפירס
על גבי קינופות פסולה. o shepireis al gabi kinofot psula. Okay, so
the Mishnah משנה Mishnah says that if you spread it
on top of the like four poster, you know the four poles,
which is what the kinofot קינופות kinofot is, it's invalid. Hatam nami
d'gavia asara התם נמי דגביה עשרה, hatam nami d'gavia asara, that's only
so Shmuel שמואל Shmuel says that would only be when it's ten
tefachim טפחים tefachim high. Veha lo tani hachi והא לא תני הכי,
veha lo tani hachi, but that wasn't what the baraita ברייתא baraita
teaches. Ditanya דתניא, ditanya, we taught in a baraita ברייתא, baraita, naklitin
shnayim נקליטין שנים. naklitin shnayim. The naklitin נקליטין naklitin which is okay
are two poles at opposite ends of the bed, so you know
it forms a tepee because if you have a bar between them.
Ve'kinofot arba'ah וקינופות ארבעה, ve'kinofot arba'ah, the kinofot קינופות kinofot is like
a four poster bed. Pireis al gabi kinofot psula פירס על גבי
קינופות פסולה, pireis al gabi kinofot psula, spread on the kinofot קינופות
kinofot it's invalid because it creates a roof on top. Al gabi
naklitin ksheira על גבי נקליטין כשירה, al gabi naklitin ksheira, on the
naklitin נקליטין naklitin where it makes a tepee it's okay. Uvilvad shelo
yiheyu naklitin gevohim min hamitah asara ובלבד שלא יהו נקליטין גבוהים מן
המטה עשרה, ubilvad shelo yiheyu naklitin gevohim min hamitah asara, provided that
the naklitin נקליטין naklitin are not ten tefachim טפחים tefachim off of
the bed. Which basically means that either criteria is enough to invalidate.
Hey welcome back. Either ten tefachim טפחים tefachim or a roof, not
that you need both to invalidate. Either is enough to invalidate. So
the Gemara גמרא Gemara says mikhlal מכלל mikhlal and from that you
can infer de'kinofot דקינופות de'kinofot when you have the four posters and
you have the roof af al pi she'ein gavoha asara אף על
פי שאין גבוהה עשרה, af al pi she'ein gavoha asara, thank you
so much, even though it is not ten tefachim טפחים tefachim high.
One or the other, either roof or ten tefachim טפחים tefachim is
enough to invalidate, as opposed to what Shmuel שמואל Shmuel said which
is you need both criteria to invalidate. So the Gemara גמרא Gemara
says no, shani kinofot de'kvi'i שאני קינופות דקביעי. shani kinofot de'kvi'i. Kinofot
קינופות kinofot are different. These poles attached to a bed are more
fixed, it's not as like of a temporary type of a pup
tent you know, it's a real like fixed feature and as a
fixed feature we're going to be strict and therefore Shmuel שמואל Shmuel
was talking about a more temporary tent. A more temporary tent you
needed two things, you needed a roof and it to be ten
tefachim טפחים tefachim high to be a problem. A more type of
a fixed feature, an attachment to a bed, there it's going to
be invalid with one or the other, either ten tefachim טפחים tefachim
high even if it's a tepee or a roof even lower. Okay,
so the difference whether you need two criteria or one is a
question about whether it is a fixed type of a tent or
a highly temporary one. We're on yud amud bet י' עמוד ב'
yud amud bet near the bottom. So the Gemara גמרא Gemara says
like this. Veharei sukkah al gabi hasukkah והרי סוכה על גבי הסוכה.
veharei sukkah al gabi hasukkah. What about a Sukkah סוכה Sukkah on
top of a Sukkah סוכה, Sukkah, which we know is invalid. Dekvi'i
דקביעי, dekvi'i, that's obviously a more fixed structure, you're not like moving
one Sukkah סוכה Sukkah away from the other. It's very
fixed. Ve'amar Shmuel ואמר שמואל, ve'amar Shmuel, and Shmuel שמואל, Shmuel, well
it's the same Shmuel שמואל, Shmuel, but Shmuel שמואל Shmuel said ke-hichshara
kach psula כהכשרה כך פסולה, ke-hichshara kach psula, and Shmuel שמואל Shmuel
said the same way it's valid with ten tefachim טפחים, tefachim, it
invalidates with ten tefachim טפחים. tefachim. So how is so there is
so so so you see the Shmuel שמואל Shmuel is consistent. Shmuel
שמואל Shmuel says to create a problem like there are two types
of problems, one is you have two kosher schach כשר סכך kosher
schach but it's a special invalidity we learned of yesterday Sukkah tachas
Sukkah סוכה תחת סוכה. Sukkah tachas Sukkah. Everything is really totally kosher
but somehow a double Sukkah סוכה, Sukkah, the bottom one is invalid.
And there we said that the height for the top one to
invalidate the bottom one is it has to be ten tefachim טפחים
tefachim removed. That's what Shmuel שמואל Shmuel said. The same Shmuel שמואל
Shmuel said that when you have something which logically is even more
problematic, you're in a tent inside your Sukkah סוכה Sukkah so you're
really in an invalid space
right, you're not
under a. That's fine, but we just said in order to resolve
שמואל Shmuel with a contradiction that when it's a fixed feature, even
one of the criteria is enough, either roof or ten טפחים. tefachim.
So is that true, why by the סוכה Sukkah under the סוכה
Sukkah do you need both criteria? Obviously it has a roof and
you have ten טפחים. tefachim. So the גמרא Gemara says no, אמר
Amar you can say התם דלמיפסל סוכה בעשרה. Hasam di-lifsol Sukkah b-asara.
There basically
there you have a כשר kosher סוכה Sukkah and it's invalidating the
סוכה Sukkah below it. So there you're gonna need a really serious
סוכה Sukkah above to invalidate the one below. You need ten טפחים.
tefachim. You need something that both has the roof and ten טפחים
tefachim and something that functions as a real סוכה Sukkah above if
you want it to invalidate the one below because it's the principle
of סוכה תחת סוכה, Sukkah tachat Sukkah, so the top thing has
to be a
סוכה. Sukkah. הכא דלשרויי אהלה, Hacha d-ishruye ohala, here you're in a
tent inside of a סוכה. Sukkah. You don't have to call the
thing you're inside a סוכה, Sukkah, the thing you're inside isn't a
סוכה Sukkah anyway, it's a tent. So you don't need the same
criteria.
You just have to say you're basically in a separate zone, you're
not underneath your סוכה. Sukkah. So בציר מעשרה נמי הוי אהלה, b-tzir
mi-asara nami havei ohala, we could be strict even less than ten
טפחים tefachim if it is a fixed type of a tent. Okay,
so again what are we saying? We're saying the special invalidity which
is a little bit hard to understand what the whole problem is,
a double-decker סוכה, Sukkah, that we can make high demands until it
invalidates. The top thing has to be ten טפחים tefachim high, it
has to have a roof, we even discussed yesterday maybe it has
to be fit for living in it, the floor won't collapse when
you try to go into the double-decker סוכה, Sukkah, that's in order
for that special invalidity. Now we're dealing though with something which is
a more obvious problem: you're in a tent in your סוכה, Sukkah,
you're really in your סוכה, Sukkah, or is the roof on top
of you is your tent, maybe you're not considered in your סוכה.
Sukkah. So שמואל Shmuel says the general rule there is two criteria:
ten טפחים tefachim high and a טפח tefach and a roof, not
a tippy. But with these contradictions we say that when you have
something more fixed, not like a pop tent, but something more fixed,
then even one of those criteria will be enough to invalidate. Okay,
אמר רב תחליפא בר אבימי אמר שמואל. Amar Rav Tachlifa bar Avimi
Amar Shmuel. Now another statement in the name of שמואל Shmuel and
you'll see it's of a similar vein.
הישן בכילה ערום מוציא ראשו חוץ לכילה וקורא קריאת שמע. Ha-yashen b-kila
arum motzi rosho chutz l-kila v-kore keryat shema. So if you're in
a כילה, kila, which is again this type of a
temporary pop tent which
has a roof on top but is less than ten טפחים tefachim
high, so that's the one that שמואל Shmuel would say if you're
in that in a סוכה Sukkah it doesn't invalidate because it's temporary
and it's less than ten טפחים tefachim high. Similarly if you're sleeping
in your bed that's covered by this pop tent and you're naked
in your bed and you stick your head outside of the tent
and the rest of your body is in the tent, you can
say קריאת שמע. keryat shema. Why? Because why don't you say what
do you mean say קריאת שמע? keryat shema? You're naked! No, because
the whole point of שמואל Shmuel is is that this type of
a pop
tent, it's temporary, it's less than ten טפחים, tefachim, so it's considered
basically not like you're under a tent, it's considered basically just like
you're under a sheet, just a little air between you and the
sheet, but it's not considered to create a separate house or separate
space and you're naked in that
space, you're basically no, you're clothed, you're cloaked with this tent. All
right, and therefore you can just stick your head outside. Now you
might say even if you're cloaked with it, if you're wearing let's
say a robe and there's nothing underneath, we have a normal halachic
principle that that's not enough, that you need something separating your heart
from your genital area, לבו רואה את הערווה, libo ro'eh et ha-ervah,
you know like you need a belt or the band of your
underwear. So if you take a quick look at תוספות, Tosafot, he
says מוציא ראשו חוץ לכילה, motzi rosho chutz l-kila, לחיא שמואל לבו
רואה את הערווה. l-chaya Shmuel libo ro'eh et ha-ervah. שמואל Shmuel doesn't
hold that's a problem. Okay, so you're basically naked underneath a robe,
the robe here is being called a כילה, kila, or the כילה
kila is being called a robe. But that's the same idea, it's
not considered a tent, it's considered just a covering on you. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says מתיבי, metivei, they ask you on this,
הישן בכילה ערום לא יוציא ראשו חוץ לכילה ויקרא קריאת שמע. ha-yashen
b-kila arum lo yotzi rosho chutz l-kila v-yikra keryat shema. We have
a ברייתא baraita that says explicitly you're not allowed to do it.
So the גמרא Gemara says הכא במאי עסקינן כשגבוה עשרה, hacha mai
askinan k'she-gavoha asara, same answer as before. Fine, that's when it's higher
than ten. That's when he admits that that's obviously a separate that's
obviously like a tent and a separate space, not something that's just
covering you. הכי נמי מסתברא, Hachi nami mistabra, you know what? That
makes sense. That that when the ברייתא baraita says it's invalid it's
when it's ten טפחים tefachim high. Why? מדקתני סיפא, mi-de-katani seifa, the
end says, הלמה זה דומה, ha-lamah zeh domeh, the end says what's
this like sticking your head out from outside of your tent when
it's invalid, what's that
like? לעומד בבית ערום שלא יוציא ראשו חוץ לחלון ויקרא קריאת שמע.
L-omed b-bayit arum she-lo yotzi rosho chutz l-chalon v-yikra keryat shema. You
can't just stick your head outside of a window. So it doesn't
help. So what? You're you're under a tent. If you're naked in
your house, you're still naked, it's not clothing. So since it compares
the tent reality with the house reality, presumably we're dealing with some
similar type of a scenario, and therefore שמואל Shmuel says that that's
that that is ten. You know, that adds credence to the claim
that we're talking about a tent that's ten טפחים tefachim high. If
the tent was lower, it would not make much sense to compare
it to the case of the house. שמע מינה, Shma mina, so
that is a that is a good point. Okay, yes, it's a
good point, that when it's ten טפחים tefachim high, that that this
idea that the כילה kila is a separate zone is only when
it is ten טפחים tefachim high. And now the גמרא Gemara says
ובבית נמי, Uvevayis nami, by the way, don't get us mixed don't
confuse
the comparison of a house to the tent. The tent has to
be ten טפחים tefachim high because as we said, when it's impermanent,
when it's more temporary and, you know, sort of like a pup
tent thing, it needs two criteria: ten טפחים tefachim and a roof.
A house is more permanent. So therefore אף על פי שאין גבוה
עשרה, af al pi she'ein gavoha asara, if you had a house
not less than ten טפחים tefachim high, I don't know what type
of a house would be less than ten טפחים tefachim high, but
whatever, you had a permanent structure less than
ten טפחים tefachim high, כיון דקביע, keivan dekavia, since it's fixed, אהלא
הוא, ohala hu, then it is an אהל, ohel, דלא גרע מקינופות,
delo gara mikinofos, it's not different from the case of the posts.
Okay?
Meaning and רש״י, Rashi, by the way, points in and I don't
know if you sort of picked up, that that's sort of like
a later gloss. You know, that sort of like you hear the,
you know, it's like the answer and then then it seems like
there's like a later gloss here that try that's just making sure
we connected all the dots. Like oh yeah, we already pointed out
that if it's permanent, then even if it's less than ten טפחים,
tefachim, so let me just make a point that the comparison of
the כילה kila to the house shouldn't be confused, and the house,
by the way, if it's less than ten טפחים tefachim is also
going to be a problem. So, what have we said now? We
said the משנה Mishna says that if you're under a roofed tent,
it's invalid. שמואל Shmuel limits it, שמואל Shmuel says only when you
have two criteria: ten טפחים tefachim and a roof. Okay, but because
of different things that he has to reconcile, he has said that
that's only in a case when it's temporary. Something that's more fixed
and established like a house or like the posters of a bed,
the poles on a on a bed which is not like just
a pup tent you open it and you close it or whatever,
those things even one of the two criteria would make it considered
like you're in a separate space, in a separate tent and therefore
it would be invalid. Either ten טפחים tefachim high or a rooftop.
Okay? Teepee ten טפחים tefachim high is a problem, rooftop less than
ten טפחים tefachim is a problem. לישנא אחרינא, Lishna achrina, now here's
another version of the similar discussion. And from here to the משנה
Mishna it's going to be pretty similar, you know, with a little
with some variation. אמרי לה, Amri lah, here's a different version the
way they say this over. אמר רב
יהודה אמר שמואל, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, says רב יהודה Rav
Yehuda in the name of שמואל, Shmuel, מותר
לישן בכילת חתנים בסוכה, mutar lishan bechilas chasanim besukkah, you can dwell
in a כילת חתנים kilas chasanim in a סוכה, Sukkah, לפי שאין
לה גג, lefi she'ein lah gag, אף על פי שגבוה עשרה. af
al pi shegavoha asara. So here it's different. Before it said he
said even though it has a roof, it's okay if it's less
than ten.
Here it is saying okay, if it doesn't have a roof, it's
okay even though it's higher than ten. Do people hear it's basically
the flip, right, of the of what we said before? Before we
said if it has a roof it's okay if it's less than
ten, here we said if it doesn't have a roof it's okay
even though it's higher than ten, which basically boils down to: to
be a problem you need both, right? You need both criteria. You
need ten and a roof. So here he's saying the flip side:
that even though it's ten, if it doesn't have a roof, meaning
if it comes to a point, if it's a teepee, it's okay.
מיתיבי, Meisivi, says the גמרא, Gemara, I'll ask you on this: הישן
בכילה בסוכה לא יצא ידי חובתו, hayishan bechila besukkah lo yatza yedei
chovaso, if you're in this tent you're it's not good. No, הכא
במאי עסקינן בששי לה גג, hacha bemai askinan besheyesh lah gag, fine.
That's the case where definitely it's ten, but it has a roof.
תא שמע, Ta shema, let's learn, נקליטין שנים וקינופות ארבע, naklitin shenayim
vekinofos arba, the נקליטין naklitin which are good are two posts, so
it's a teepee, the קינופות kinofos are four, so it's a tent.
אגב פירש על גבי קינופות פסולה. agav pirsh al gabi kinofos pesula.
If you do it on the קינופות kinofos on the, then it's
not good, you have a roof. על גבי נקליטין כשירה, al gabei
naklitin kesheira, on the נקליטין naklitin it's okay because it's a teepee.
ובלבד שלא יהיו נקליטין גבוהים מן המטה עשרה, uvelvad shelo yehyu naklitin
gevohim min hamita asara, as long as it's not ten טפחים tefachim
high. So this one is the ברייתא braisa we had we started
with before that says either criteria is enough. Even if it's a
even if it's a teepee, ten טפחים tefachim high is a problem.
So if that's true, that was שמואל's Shmuel case. שמואל Shmuel said
ten טפחים tefachim is not a problem when it's a teepee. This
says ten טפחים tefachim is a problem even if it's a teepee.
Says the גמרא, Gemara, הגבוהים מן המטה עשרה פסולה, hagvohim min hamita
asara pesula, so you see once it's ten טפחים tefachim high it's
invalid אף על פי שאין לה גג, af al pi she'ein lah
gag, although it doesn't have a roof, even though it's a teepee,
which is against what שמואל Shmuel said. No, same answer, שאני נקליטין
דקביעי, shani naklitin dekavi'i, the נקליטין naklitin are different, they're fixed to
the bed and therefore because it's more fixed, ten טפחים tefachim is
a problem even without a even without a roof. So again, שמואל
Shmuel said to be a problem you need two things: ten טפחים
tefachim and a roof. Okay? But that was his כילה kila case.
In the earlier version he emphasized even though it has a roof
it's not a problem if it's not ten, here he's saying even
though it's ten it's not a problem if it's not a roof.
But basically it's the same point, you need both criteria. What do
you do with the ברייתא braisa that speaks about the posters to
the bed, the poles on the bed, that says that
even- So the גמרא Gemara says אי קבי ei kavei if it's
more permanent ליהוי כי קינופות lehei ke'kinofot why isn't it as bad
as the קינופות? kinofot? The קינופות kinofot the four poles are a
problem even lower than ten טפחים. tefachim. Why is this a problem
only higher than ten טפחים? tefachim? The two poles? So it says
no, לגבי קינופות לא קבי legabei kinofot lo kavei relative to the
קינופות kinofot it's less permanent. ולגבי קילה קבי ליה u'legabei kila kavei
lei relative to the קילה kila it's more permanent. Now there actually
was an easier answer because the four which תוספות Tosafot points out,
the four poles you have a roof. That's why it's a bigger
problem. But again, but we just assume that's what the גמרא Gemara
means. So again, you have your two scenarios, right? You've
got your tent here, you know, which is ten טפחים tefachim high,
but it comes to a roof. And
then you've got your normal thing which is, I don't know, we'll
call it nine טפחים tefachim high,
okay, but so this has a roof, this is טפח tefach
that has a roof. This has the י' טפחים. yud tefachim. Okay,
but אין לו טפח. ein lo tefach. Okay.
So are these a problem? Each one of these has one of
the criteria, right? This
has the roof criteria, this has the ten טפחים tefachim criteria. The
ברייתא braita basically says that each one is a problem on the
bed, that's the קינופות kinofot and the נקליטין. naklitin. Okay, this is
the קינופות? kinofot? Did I get it right?
Let's take a look. No, this is the נקליטין. naklitin.
This is the נקליטין naklitin and this is the קינופות. kinofot. The
ברייתא braita says that each one of those is a problem, either
the טפח tefach or the ten טפחים. tefachim. But שמואל Shmuel says
only both of them. And the basic answer is that שמואל's Shmuel
case, that these are all attached to a bed, okay, I guess
this would be like a side view on your bed, here's your
bed anyway, okay, these are all attached to a bed,
okay, whatever. Wow, that actually was a bad example. But you get
the idea. Anyway, these are all attached to a bed, so therefore
they're more permanent, and therefore one of the criteria is enough. שמואל's
Shmuel case is a pup tent, and in his case of a
pup tent which is less permanent or something like a pup tent,
right, therefore you're going to need both criteria, you're going to need
it to be both ten טפחים tefachim and have that.
So the גמרא Gemara says אטו קביעותא מילתא היא? Atu keviuta milta
hi? What does just permanence have to do with it? Is it
a concept of being a tent? It must be something that somewhat
touches on it. It could be that like saying one of the
criteria is only a דרבנן, d'rabbanan, that the real דאורייתא d'oraita problem
requires both, but once it's more permanent we're going to rabbinically demand
only one. It's not logical why just because it's more permanent, if
the two features combined make it a tent, why one feature becomes
more of a thing once it's more permanent. It does not make
sense. Okay. But anyway, first I'm going to redraw something. A better
example here.
Which is the קילה? kila?
So the קילה kila is not being drawn here. These are like
attached to a bed. A קילה kila would be a similar type
of a canopy, but it would be more like a, you know,
like a pup... like something you, you know, you spread out and
then you remove. It is draped over.
There's nice pictures here.
Right, like a pup... it is draped over, but it's not like
physically, it's not a part of the bed, right?
The קילה kila is at the דובנא? duvna? Yeah. How's that different
from the...?
Because one is like a tent that you come in and it's
portable and you open it up and then you remove it. This
is a permanent part of the bed. This is just attached to
the bed. Okay.
Is there another case where the upright canopy comes to a point
on the bottom? What? Is there another case in the גמרא Gemara
we discussed where this upright canopy comes to a point at the
top?
That's what this is.
Oh, that's the... I thought that's the tent.
No, I mean, both of these are cases on a bed, okay,
they're both like, you know, again, you sort of imagine...
oh, okay, I see.
Right. You imagine... those are both different ways of being over a
bed, but it's more... you know, think, I don't know, think about
the קילה kila like mosquito netting or something. These are like a
fixture on the bed. Okay? So therefore those only one is enough,
only one invalidates, whereas שמואל Shmuel requires both to invalidate. So now
the גמרא Gemara says like this: דרש רבא בר רב הונא. Darash
Rava bar Rav Huna. So with all those things, okay, at least
שמואל Shmuel everybody would agree that with two criteria it's invalid. But
comes along רבא בר רב הונא Rava bar Rav Huna and he
teaches: מותר לישון בקילה Mutar lishon b'kila אף על פי שיש לה
גג af al pi she'yesh la gag אף על פי שגבוהה עשרה.
af al pi she'gvoha asara. You can sleep in a קילה, kila,
it's ten טפחים tefachim high, it has a roof, fine! I mean,
it's crazy. What do you do about all the ברייתות braitot and
משניות mishnayot that we quoted before? So the גמרא Gemara ah, says
it actually will work out according to a particular opinion. כמאן? K'man?
Who is this going by? כרבי יהודה, K'Rabbi Yehuda, like רבי יהודה.
Rabbi Yehuda. דאמר לא אתי אהל עראי ומבטל אהל קבע. D'amar lo
ati ohel arai u'mevatel ohel keva.
A temporary tent does not come and negate a permanent tent. Now
you all remember that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is identified as one
of the opinions that sees a סוכה succa as being permanent, as
סוכה דירת קבע. succa dirat keva. And that's probably relevant. And all
these things, your bed inside your סוכה, succa, right, a canopy over
a bed is temporary relative to, although we've been calling it more
permanent than a pup tent, it's still temporary. you relative to the
סוכה Sukkah structure. And therefore he says, if you're in a bed
under a canopy in a סוכה Sukkah and somebody said, "Where are
you?" you wouldn't say, "I'm under my canopy." You'd say, "I'm in
my סוכה," Sukkah, right? So therefore he says, that does not define
you as being in a separate space. It's only a temporary relative
to the סוכה Sukkah which is permanent. Okay. So he says like
this: דתנן, De-tnan, we taught in a משנה, Mishna, אמר ר' יהודה,
Amar Rebbe Yehuda, נוהגים היינו לישן תחת המיטה בפני הזקנים, Nohegim hayinu
lishan tachas hamitah bifnei hazekenim, we would sleep underneath the bed in
front of the elders and they never said anything to us during
סוכות Sukkos in the סוכה Sukkah and they never said it was
a problem. So you see, it's okay. And you could have said
the ten טפחים, tefachim, different types of things, but the גמרא Gemara
understands that it's a general principle that it is never a problem.
So the גמרא Gemara says ולימא הלכה כר' יהודה, velaima halachah ke-Rebbe
Yehuda, so if he—that's what he's basing himself on—why say, "Oh, you
can sleep in a כילה kilah even though it's ten טפחים, tefachim,
even though it has a גג?" gag? Just say, "Oh, we rule
like that ר' יהודה Rebbe Yehuda of the משנה." Mishna. No, cause
that ר' יהודה Rebbe Yehuda of the משנה Mishna is not as
obviously as... as strong as the statement that was made. אי אמרת
הלכה כר' יהודה, Ee amart halachah ke-Rebbe Yehuda, had you just said
we rule like ר' יהודה, Rebbe Yehuda, הוה אמינא havah amina I
would have said הני מילי מיטה דלגבה עשויה, hani milei mitah de-legavah
asuya,
fine, if you're under a bed, I'm not going to say you're
in a separate space, you're under a separate roof cause the bed
is made for sleeping on top of it. So being under a
bed, right, you don't say the space under a bed is naturally
defined as like a separate zone, a separate area, okay? It's not
like it's made to serve as a roof to the area below
it. אבל כילה דלתוכה עשויה, Aval kilah de-letochah asuya, a canopy that
is made for the area below to serve as a roof to
the area below, אימא לא, ayma lo, maybe we would not be
lenient, maybe in that case we would say you are under a
different roof and you're not under the roof of a סוכה. Sukkah.
קמשמע לן, Kamashma lan, so he's teaching us טעמיה דר' יהודה, ta'amei
de-Rebbe Yehuda, the reasoning of ר' יהודה, Rebbe Yehuda, דלא אתי עראי
מבטל ליה אקבע, de-lo ati arai mevatel leh a-keva, that it is
a categorical principle, the סוכה Sukkah is always קבע, keva, all these
things are considered temporary tents and it... it does not negate it,
meaning it doesn't make it like you're under a different roof. Fundamentally,
you're under the roof of the סוכה. Sukkah. לא שנא מיטה ולא
שנא כילה, Lo shena mitah ve-lo shena kilah, it doesn't matter whether
you're talking about a bed or whether you're talking about a כילה.
kilah. Okay, interesting question. Can you eat under a table in your
סוכה? Sukkah? All right, so... so that would be based on this.
And now who we rule like? So if you take a look
at תוספות, Tosafos, מותר לישן בכילת חתנים בסוכה אף על פי שיש
לה גג אף על פי שגבוהה עשרה אין הלכה כן. mutar lishan
be-kilas chasanim be-sukkah af pi she-yesh lah gag af pi she-gevohah asarah
ein halachah ken. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara basically has to identify
this with ר' יהודה. Rebbe Yehuda. We do not rule that way
and we rule that you can not. Okay, but... it might be
if it's like underneath the table and something so temporary, that's like
the כילה, kilah, you would need two things: a טפח tefach and
ten טפחים. tefachim. I don't know, a table has a טפח, tefach,
does it have ten טפחים, tefachim, three feet under the table, 30
inches? Probably not.
It's a little lower...
little lower... most tables.
Okay, but that's...
that would have to be a twist on that famous חסידיש chasidish
story about the guy who was under the table, right? The... the
famous... okay, whatever, yeah. Like he goes down, he thinks he's a
chicken, he... anyway.
Okay,
so this creates an interesting question for שבת. Shabbos. How can we
set up folding...
ah, excellent, I was going to reference that, right? The whole idea
about you can't make an אהל ohel on שבת, Shabbos, how do
you create a folding table? So there's a lot of specifics about
that, but one of the most basic differences is exactly what the
גמרא Gemara said here. Fundamentally, it's not considered an אהל ohel because
it's not made for the space below it, it's made to serve
the space above it. Okay, so that actually is a major reason
why that's okay. Same by a folding chair and so on. Other
reasons as well, but okay, so it's on hinges, so it naturally
opens and closes. Anyway, fine. Let's look at the next משנה Mishna
and we quoted this earlier. הדלה עליה את הגפן ואת הדלעת, Hidlah
alehah es ha-gefen ve-es ha-dilaas,
you sort of bent over your סוכה Sukkah a... a grape vine
or a gourd. I always wonder why it gives the example of
a gourd. I mean, a gourd I guess cause it covers a
lot of area, but you're not bending the gourd, you're bending I
guess the vine, and now the gourd is... is serving as סכך.
schach. A gourd sort of grows like, gourds grow... they must grow
above the ground, right? They're not... so... it's a fruit. Okay. ואת
הקיסום Ve-es ha-kissom or the קיסום, kissom, I don't know how they
translate קיסום kissom there. רש"י Rashi says it's a type of a
vine, ivy. Oh, ivy, really? Okay.
תוספות Tosafos says ivy. Interesting. Okay. And
there's a picture of a gourd here.
Excellent. Okay. And now you put the סכך schach and you used
that to be the סכך schach on top of the סוכה. Sukkah.
So basically you have stuff that's still attached to the ground. פסולה,
Psulah, it's invalid cause it's not enough that it grows from the
ground, it has to be detached. ואם היה סכך הרבה מהם, Ve-im
hayah schach harbeh mei-hem,
but if you added סכך schach and there's a majority of kosher
סכך, schach, okay? And before we discussed the issue about like if
you like mix it together, so it's not that everything is in
a distinct zone, then it all gets looked at as a unit
and you go by the majority. So having a majority of kosher
סכך, schach, again, if things are mixed together, that's one way to
make it fine. And we discussed that earlier. And now we're going
to look at the second part which we did not discuss earlier.
או שקצצן, O she-ketzatzan, if you actually cut them, you had the
vine was over the סוכה, Sukkah, the gourd was over... of the
סוכה, Sukkah, and then you just chopped, cut the vine, okay, and
now it's detached, כשרה, kesherah, that's principle. Now, זה הכלל, Ze hachlal,
this is the principle: כל שמקבל טומאה ואין גידולו מן הארץ, kol
she-mekabel tumah v'ein gidulo min ha-aretz, anything that can is susceptible for
becoming טמא tamei like a vessel or food that has water that
has come in contact with it after it's been cut, and it
does not grow from the ground, means or it does not grow
from the ground, אין מסככין בו, ein mesach'chin bo, you cannot use
it for סכך. s'chach. וכל דבר שאינו מקבל טומאה וגידולו מן הארץ,
V'chol davar she-eino mekabel tumah v'gidulo min ha-aretz, but if it both
does not is not cannot become טמא, tamei, is not a vessel,
and number two, it also grew from the ground, and also it's
like I said, not food that came in contact with water, then
מסככין בו, mesach'chin bo, you can use it for סכך. s'chach. By
the way, the food not in contact with water is interesting because
that's something that will become טמא tamei once it comes in contact
with water, so just because right now it cannot become טמא, tamei,
that sort of gets ruled out as well, anything that could be
in that category of being potentially susceptible for becoming טמא. tamei. Anyway,
let's take a look at the גמרא, Gemara, because the גמרא Gemara
is going to focus on the case of cutting the vine after
the סכך s'chach is already on it. יתיב רב יוסף קמיה דרב
כהנא, Yativ Rav Yosef kamey d'Rav Kahana, so רב יוסף Rav Yosef
was sitting in front of רב כהנא. Rav Kahana. יתיב וקאמר, Yativ
v'ka'amar, and he was sitting and he was saying, או שקצצן כשרה,
o she-ketzatzan kesherah, if you cut it it's כשרה, kesherah, the vine.
ואמר רב, Va'amar Rav, but רב Rav says, not really. צריך לנענע,
Tzarich l'na'anea, so you have to even after you've cut the vine,
you have to like move the סכך s'chach a little bit. Why?
Because there's a general problem which you might be familiar with called
תעשה ולא מן העשוי. ta'aseh v'lo min ha-asuy. חג הסוכות תעשה לך,
Chag ha-Sukkot ta'aseh lecha, okay,
we're going to see it by ציצית tzitzit as well, the פסוק
pasuk says גדילים תעשה לך, gedilim ta'aseh lecha, that
when you make it into the object of a מצוה, mitzvah, it
has to be actively made, not somehow indirectly
something happened and then all of a sudden it came into existence.
What would be that example? So, the classic example is is that
you have a haystack and you dig a hole in the haystack
and now you have a סוכה, Sukkah, right? But the roof, remember,
סוכות Sukkot primarily focuses on סכך. s'chach. So if you have to
make the סכך, s'chach, you didn't actually make the סכך. s'chach. You
made the cavity and the סכך s'chach came into existence, okay, that
would not be good. Even though we said, remember, סוכה Sukkah does
not have to be made for the sake of the חג, chag,
it only has to be made for the sake of giving shade.
It could be made by non-Jews, it could be made for animals.
Yes, but it has to be made. The סכך s'chach has to
be made, not just indirectly you did something else and then it
popped into existence. Okay, so therefore, here's going to be the question:
you bent a סכך s'chach over the roof, you bent the gourd
over the roof, that was your act of making, but it wasn't
yet כשר kasher סכך. s'chach. You cut it, it became כשר kasher
סכך, s'chach, but was it made? It was it
had already been made, but it was invalid, and when it became
valid, it wasn't being made. So, it shouldn't be good. That's the
question.
Yes, תעשה ולא מן העשוי ta'aseh v'lo min ha-asuy applies to if
you if you put סכך s'chach up first, right, and then build
the wall?
Excellent question. So, that's actually a מחלוקת הפוסקים. machlokas haposkim. If you
put the סכך s'chach up and then you do the walls, so
the סכך s'chach is made, but the סוכה Sukkah isn't כשרה kesherah
yet, right? So, that actually is is actually debated in the פוסקים
poskim whether that's good or not. And that's actually very relevant because
with our modern סוכות Sukkot that would be very easy to do,
right? You make the frame, throw up the סכך, s'chach, and then
you put up the walls, right. So,
then you could just lift it up and down. Right,
but that's the question whether that's necessary. So רב Rav says, you
know what, cutting it isn't enough, you have to move it a
little bit. If that's true, there's not much of a חידוש chiddush
in the משנה. Mishnah. Maybe the חידוש chiddush is you don't have
to like literally take it off and put it back on, just
a little bit of moving is enough. Maybe lift it up a
טפח, tefach, not exactly clear how much.
So, that's what that's what רב יוסף Rav Yosef was saying. אמר
ליה רב הונא, Amar lei Rav Huna, so רב הונא Rav Huna
says, השמואל אמרה, ha-Shmuel amrah, that's not רב, Rav, that's שמואל Shmuel
who said that. הדרנהו רב יוסף לאפיה, Hadrinhu Rav Yosef l'apeih, so
רב יוסף Rav Yosef turned his face away from him, he got
really angry. ואמר ליה, V'amar lei, אטו מי קאמינא לך דלא אמר
שמואל, atu mi ka'amina lach d'la amar Shmuel,
what are you doing contradicting me? I didn't say שמואל Shmuel didn't
say it. אמר רב ואמר שמואל, Amar Rav v'amar Shmuel, רב Rav
said it and שמואל Shmuel said it. Don't say no, שמואל Shmuel
said it. They agree on.
Yeah, but he's saying what what what are you doing correcting me?
I said רב Rav said it, and שמואל Shmuel also said it.
Don't correct me. So, ואמר שמואל אמר
ליה רב הונא, v'amar Shmuel amar lei Rav Huna, רב הונא Rav
Huna said back to him, you misunderstood me, I was correcting you.
הכי קאמינא לך, hachi ka'amina lach, this is what I was saying
to you.
דשמואל אמרה ולא רב, d'Shmuel amrah v'lo Rav, that's a position of
שמואל Shmuel and it's not a position of רב. Rav. רב Rav
actually would say you don't have to move the סכך, s'chach, you
could just cut it and it would be okay. Why? דרב אכשורי
מכשר, d'Rav achshorei machshar, רב Rav would say that case is כשר.
kasher. כי הא דרב עמרם חסידא, Ki ha d'Rav Amram Chasida, like
a similar story with רב עמרם חסידא, Rav Amram Chasida,
רמא תכלתא לפרזומא דאינשי ביתיה. rama tcheilata l'farzuma d'inshei beiteih. He put
תכלת, tcheiles, now תכלת tcheiles is a word that is a represents
means ציצית tzitzit because it focuses doesn't mean just the תכלת. tcheilet.
There's actually an English word for that for a for a for
a something that a piece of something represents the whole. You know
what I'm talking about? Anyway, some literary term. Anyway, תכלת tcheiles in
the גמרא Gemara means ציצית, tzitzit, okay, most of the time like
in this context, not always. So he put ציצית tsitsis for the
פרזומא, parzuma, for the טלית tallis of אינשי ביתיה, inshei beisai, the
people of his household, which people of his household generally means the
women, his wife. So, interesting in what's going on right now in
the last two weeks in the Jewish community. He was making ציצית
tsitsis for his wife. He felt that women are obligated in ציצית.
tsitsis. It's not limited to the daytime; it applies at night as
well. So he was making ציצית tsitsis for his wife.
Okay. תלאן ולא פסק ראשי חוטים שלהן. Tlaan velo pasak roshei chutim
shelahen. He suspended them, which means he stuck them in the hole,
okay, he inserted them, but he did not cut the heads of
them.
So what does that mean? It means if you know how, like
if you imagine a string, fold over a long string like four
times, right? Fold it over four times. You have like four ends,
but at two of the ends they're looped. They're not really four
strings; it's really one big string folded over four times. Take that,
put it through the hole of the ציצית, tsitsis, use the loose
thing to do all the knots and all the winding. And now
you have a whole thing of ציצית tsitsis really made with one
string. And after you're done, if you snip the loops, then you're
gonna get your four strings. But when you're making it, it's one
string, not four strings, okay? So that's what he did.
אתא לקמיה דרב חייא בר אשי. Asa lekamei deRav Chiya bar Ashi.
He came in front of רב חייא בר אשי. Rav Chiya bar
Ashi. אמר ליה הכי אמר רב: Amar lei hachi amar Rav: מפסקין
והן כשרים. mifaskun vehein ksheirin.
Sure, you can snip them and they'll be fine. The act of
snipping them and making them into four strings is the act of
making them into ציצית. tsitsis. Okay. So that actually is valid. Presumably
it's not תעשה ולא מן העשוי taaseh velo min heasuy because it
required an act. Although the act was not the physical act of
making, the act was the halachic act—but it wasn't the physical act
of like putting them in the hole and twisting or whatever, but
it was a physical act and it made them kosher. That is
considered the act of making. Okay. So yes, and the same is
by snipping the gourd off of the vine, right? It is a
physical act. It's not done to the gourd itself, but it's done
to the vine, but it's done to—but it wasn't an act of
putting the gourd on the סוכה, sukkah, but it was a physical
act. It did make it valid. That is considered an act of
making the object. Okay. So that's what רב Rav says. מפסקין mifaskun
cut them והן כשרים vehein ksheirin they'll be kosher. אמר פסיקתן זו
היא עשייתן. Amar psikasun zu hi asiyasun. The cutting of them is
the making of them, even though it was not the winding of
the string and putting it in the hole, it was a physical
act done that made it valid, that is considered making it. הכא
נמי חיתוך צריכתן זו היא עשייתן Hacha nami chisuch tzerichasun zu hi
asiyasun cutting the vine is the making of the סכך. sechach. So
רב Rav would actually say, and that's actually the more פשט pshat
of the משנה, mishnah, that it's sufficient to cut it.
Okay. וסבר שמואל. Usavar Shmuel. So now the גמרא Gemara says, does
שמואל Shmuel hold לא אמרינן פסיקתן זו היא עשייתן, la amrinan psikasun
zu hi asiyasun, does שמואל Shmuel disagree with that? Cutting it is
not making it? והתני שמואל משום רבי חייא. Vehatni Shmuel mishum Rabbi
Chiya. שמואל Shmuel himself teaches in the name of רבי חייא: Rabbi
Chiya: הידק לשתי
קרנות בבת אחת. Hidak lishtei kranos bebvas achas. Basically what you did
is you took the two corners of your garment and you put
them together and you put your four strings of ציצית tsitsis between
the two corners of your garment, right? You get like the holes,
right? So we have an example, anyway, here.
Take off my jacket, let's do a little show and demonstration. What
you did was, right,
you put your two corners together.
You have holes in each of them, right? You put the four
strings through the holes, right? And then you go ahead and whatever,
you know, you got a lot of like loose stuff going on
here, you wrap it, you do the whole thing, but really you've
got just, you know, you don't have two sets of four strings.
You have one set of four strings and after again you're done
with the whole thing, then you snip it. Okay. It's a similar
idea that first you make it and then you snip it, and
only then does it really become the right types of strings. Alright,
so it's very similar to the other case with a variation.
ואחר כך פסק ראשי חוטים שלהן. veachar kach pasak roshei chutim shelahen.
And afterwards, only after you sort of put them through and, you
know, made them into ציצית, tsitsis, you cut them and you turn
them into two sets of strings. כשרים, Ksheirim, it's kosher. So you
see שמואל Shmuel holds also cutting it is enough. So מאי לאו
דקשר ואחר כך פסק? mai lav dekasher veachar kach pasak? Does it
not mean like I described it to you, that first you did
all the knotting and everything was done and it was still invalid,
and the last thing you did was you separated them? So you
see that act of separation was what made them. Isn't that the
scenario? So it says לא. lo. No, that's not necessarily the scenario.
שפסק ואחר כך קשר. Shepasak veachar kach kasher. First you snipped them.
The only thing you did wrong or you did unusual was you
put them through both holes at the same time, right? But as
soon as you got them through both holes, you snipped them right
at that moment. And then when you did the knotting and the
twisting, that was all, everything was totally fine, okay? So the only
thing you did wrong was the putting in the holes. מאי
למימרא? Mai lemeimra? So then what's the חידוש? chiddush? So then of
course you made it kosher because once you started with your twisting
and knotting, you had two sets of four strings. Who cares that
you... you put them in the holes at the same time. No,
מהו דתימא, mahu de-teima, I might have thought בעינן כנף בשעת פתיל?
be'inan knaf besha'at petil? And the פתיל petil means the string, the
כנף knaf is the corner. So when you have the string in
it, when you initially insert the string, it has to be one,
you know, one corner, not here where the string is in two
corners, וליכא, ve-leka, you don't have it, קא משמע לן. kama-shma lan.
So fine, I might have thought that even at the moment you
insert it in, right, it has to be, you know, it has
to be like exactly in the right form. No, you can cut,
insert it, then cut it, and then you can start your, you
know, your twists and your knots. But at least there when you're
doing your twists and your knots, you're doing an actual עשייה asiyah
and everything is כשר. kosher. So the only חידוש chidush there is
when you insert it in the hole it doesn't have to be
totally כשר kosher yet. But, but nevertheless, the knotting and the tying
and the twisting, all of that is totally כשר. kosher. That's a
real עשייה asiyah as opposed to רב Rav who says you could
wait till the very end of the process and cut it then,
and that cutting at the end will make the whole will do
will be the entire עשייה, asiyah, will be the entire making of
it. Okay, קא משמע לן kama-shma lan that you don't need that.
פשיטא. Pshita. So now I'm going to ask you on,
on רב's Rav's idea that you can cut it at the end.
תלאן ולא פסק ראשי חוטיהן, Tala'an ve-lo pasak rashei chutihen, you put
the ציצית tzitzit in the hole and you didn't cut the head.
פסולין, Psulin, it's invalid. So that's a question to רב Rav who
says you can just cut them. מאי לאו פסולין לעולם, Mai lav
psulin le-olam, doesn't that mean that they're remain פסול pasul now that
you've made them into ציצית? tzitzit? There's no way to fix it.
תיובתא דרב, Tiyuvta de-Rav, a contradiction to רב. Rav. אמר לך רב,
Amar lach Rav, רב Rav will say to you, no, מאי פסולין
פסולין עד שיפסקו. mai psulin, psulin ad she-yipasku. No, it means they're
invalid right now, but you can still fix it, just cut it,
which is pretty funny because then what's the חידוש? chidush? But okay.
The חידוש chidush is is that they have to be four separate
strings, it can't be one string folded over four times. But yeah,
fine, it just means it's invalid until you cut it. ושמואל אמר,
U-Shmuel amar, שמואל Shmuel says no, פסולין לעולם. psulin le-olam. Give me
a break. פסולין Psulin means it's totally invalid. You'd have to make
it where it's four strings, you cannot cut it at the end.
וכן אמר לוי, Ve-chen amar Levi, and that's what לוי Levi says,
פסולין לעולם, psulin le-olam, they're always invalid. I mean, of course you
could untie it and do it again, but meaning in this state
where it's already been tied and knotted, there's nothing you can do.
וכן אמר רב מתנה אמר שמואל, Ve-chen amar Rav Matna amar Shmuel,
פסולין לעולם. psulin le-olam. That's a pretty funny וכן ve-chen since it's
רב מתנה Rav Matna quoting שמואל. Shmuel. But okay. Anyway, רב Rav
is a lone voice here that says that cutting at the end
is like the making of it. Okay.
You said, you said that
in cases like that, the גמרא Gemara is usually against that?
No, I'm, what I meant was, no, no, no. No. When it
says this א A פוסק posek this and ב B and ג
C and ד D פוסק, posek, that actually supports the position. No,
what I was saying was when the גמרא Gemara says, the phrase
was specifically כולהו סבירא להו. kulhu sevira lehu. When an אמורא Amora
comes and identifies a number of different תנאים Tanna'im that are all
variations on a theme, it says so and so and so and
so and so and so כולהו סבירא להו kulhu sevira lehu X.
That's that's often said as a way of like marginalizing that position.
They're all coming from this, you know, unusual position of of X.
But this is a discussion where we're just saying he פוסק posek
this way, he פוסק, posek, he פוסק. posek. That's as opposed to
identifying distinct תנאים Tanna'im in distinct cases and saying they're all part
of a similar camp. That yeah that was what I referred to
before when אביי Abaye was identifying זיוף כסף. ziyuf kesef. Okay. So,
all right. So that's what we have. וכן אמר רב מתנה, Ve-chen
amar Rav Matna, we did that. איכא דאמרי, Ika d'amri, some say,
אמר רב מתנה בדידי הוה עובדא, amar Rav Matna, bedidi havah uvda,
this exactly happened with me, is that I did the whole folding
over and I made my ציצית tzitzit and then I needed to
cut
it, ואתאי לקמיה דמר שמואל, ve-atai le-kamieh de-Mar Shmuel, and I came
in front of שמואל, Shmuel, ואמר לי פסולין לעולם, ve-amar li psulin
le-olam, and שמואל Shmuel said I'm sorry buddy but you can't just
cut them, you gotta undo it and do the whole thing again,
it remains invalid. Okay. So basically רב Rav is is a lone
voice here.
איכא דאמרי, Ika d'amri, others say, אמר רב מתנה, amar Rav Matna,
I just said that. מיתיבי, Meitivei, I'll ask you on this. תלאן
ואחר כך פסק ראשי חוטיהן פסולין. Tala'an ve-achar kach pasak rashei chutihen
psulin. Here's another challenge on רב. Rav. It says you suspended them
and then it says and you cut them after you put them
in the hole. It says they're invalid, right? That's a real contradiction
on רב. Rav. It explicitly says even after cutting it's invalid. ותניא,
Ve-tanya, and we taught, גבי סוכה, gabei sukkah, and we talk by
סוכה, sukkah, תעשה ולא מן העשוי. ta'aseh ve-lo min ha-asuy. You shall
make, חג הסוכות תעשה, chag ha-sukkot ta'aseh, you shall make your סוכה
sukkah and not something that is already pre-made, made indirectly and not
directly made by you. מכאן אמרו, Mikan amru, and from this this
they said, הדלה עליה גפן ודלעת וקיסום, hidlah aleha gefen ve-dila'at ve-kisom,
if you bent the gourd, the vine, or the ivy on your
סוכה, sukkah, וסיכך על גבן פסולה, ve-sikach al gaban psulah, and you
put סכך sechach on them it's invalid. So היכי דמי, heichi dami,
what's the, why is that an application of the principle of תעשה
ולא מן העשוי? ta'aseh ve-lo min ha-asuy? The way it's described the
problem is that it's
פסול סכך. pasul sechach. אילימא בשלא קצצן, Ilema bi-she-lo katzatzan, if the
scenario is that you've got your gourd on your סוכה sukkah but
it hasn't been cut, מאי איריא משום תעשה ולא מן העשוי? mai
irya mishum ta'aseh ve-lo min ha-asuy? That's not an application of the
תעשה ולא מן העשוי ta'aseh ve-lo min ha-asuy principle. תיפוק ליה, Tipok
lei, learn it out מדמחובר נינהו mi-de-mechubar ninhu
that it's attached to the ground. That's the problem of the case.
So how is this being given as an example? of תעשה ולא
מן העשוי. ta'aseh v'lo min he'asui. אלא בשקצצן, ela b'she-katzatzan, the only
explanation is, is that the ברייתא's braita assuming you bent the gourd
over and then you cut it. And that's why it's the principle
of תעשה ולא מן העשוי. ta'aseh v'lo min he'asui. And that's no
good, because it was not made when it was kosher, it was
first made and then became kosher. וקתני פסולה, u-ktani psula, and it
says it's invalid. ושמע מינה דלא אמרינן קציצתן זו היא
עשייתן, u-shma mina d'lo amrinan k'tzitzatan zo hi asiyyatan, and you see
that the cutting does not make it. תיופתא דרב, tiyufta d'Rav, and
it's a contradiction to רב. Rav. So these are pretty good proofs
against רב. Rav. Let's, however, not forget that the simple sense of
the משנה Mishna supports רב. Rav. The simple sense of the משנה
Mishna says you cut it and it's kosher. Okay, and שמואל Shmuel
has to add, oh no no no, you moved the סכך s'chach
afterwards and so on. But okay, the גמרא Gemara here has some
other things that contradict רב. Rav. So אמר לך רב, amar lach
Rav, so רב Rav will tell you, הכא במאי עסקינן, hacha b'mai
askinan, what are we talking about here? דשלפינהו שלופי. d'shalfinehu shlufey. You
didn't like do it a nice snip with a scissor and really
cut it. You sort of like you sort of like yanked it
out, but it's of the ground, but it's sort of like it's
still intertwined with the vines, you know? Imagine you've got like a
heavy vine growth and, you know, you sort of pull something out
and it's still there, visibly it looks like it's still connected to
the ground. It's still like a lot of, you know, you've got
something that's like sheathed in a in bark and you pull it
out and it's still sheathed in the bark even though it's not
completely attached anymore. So that's the scenario. So vis so therefore
דלא מינכרא עשייה דידיה. d'lo minkara asiya didey. Okay, so and in
that case, it's not obvious that you've that you've actually have transformed
it. Technically it's not מחובר, mechubar, but it's not obvious. So it's
a weak answer because who cares if it's not obvious? Halachically that's
considered a making, that's considered a making. It sounds like he's creating
some דרבנן d'rabbanan problem, like it does not look obviously separate and
therefore it's going to rabbinically remain a problem because it still looks
attached. Okay, although the problem should be that it's considered attached, not
תעשה ולא מן העשוי. ta'aseh v'lo min he'asui. So he's reframing it
as if you don't do an obvious change of what the object
looks like, an obvious physical change, like, then you
then we cannot halachically call it probably let's say rabbinically, we cannot
call it like you've transformed it. You've now made the סכך. s'chach.
To say your cutting makes it means that they will only be
willing to acknowledge that if there's a visible change. If you've changed
it halachically without it being too visible, we won't consider that a
new making. So the גמרא Gemara says מכל מקום תמן והכא פסקא
קשיא. micol makom tman ve-hacha paska kashya. Fine, but that doesn't deal
with the case by the ציצית, tzitzit, which is very visible. The
case of the ציצית tzitzit says if you put the strings in
and then you cut it, it's invalid even after you cut it.
So קשיא לרב. kashya le-Rav. So it says קשיא, kashya, fine, you're
right, it's difficult. This these ברייתות, braitot, some of this evidence is
going against רב Rav and does make it sound like cutting does
not suffice. Okay, one more try. לימא כתנאי, leima kitannai, maybe we'll
say in order to a little bit back up רב, Rav, because
we have now some evidence against him, although the simple sense of
the משנה's Mishna like him, maybe this issue is a debate of
תנאים, tannaim, okay, whether cutting it is a making of it for
תעשה ta'aseh purposes. By the way, anytime the גמרא Gemara says לימא
כתנאי, leima kitannai, let's say it's like the debate of תנאים, tannaim,
means it's going to reject it. If it says כתנאי, kitannai, that
means we're going to make the assertion and stick with it that
it corresponds to a debate of תנאים. tannaim. לימא כתנאי leima kitannai
means, let's say that it is, and we're going to say, no,
it actually is not necessarily that's what's going on. Okay, but we're
going now try to find maybe some תנא tanna that supports רב.
Rav. ענביו
מרובות מעליו, anavav merubbot mealav, you have this is going on a
משנה Mishna we'll see later that you have a you have an
הדס hadas that has berries on it. I don't know if anybody
ever saw an הדס hadas with berries, you can see it sometimes,
and it says if there're too many berries, it invalidates the הדס.
hadas. Okay, so what, there's the picture, there you go. Now, you
went ahead and you plucked and you picked the berries off of
the הדס. hadas. עבר וליקטן פסול, avar ve-liktan pasul, it's invalid, דברי
רבי שמעון בן הוצדק, divrey Rabbi Shimon ben Hotzadak, that's what רבי
שמעון בן הוצדק Rabbi Shimon ben Hotzadak says. Plucking the berries doesn't
help. וחכמים מכשירים, ve-Chachamim machshirin, and the חכמים Chachamim say it's kosher.
Now that's a very bizarre debate. Why would anybody say it's invalid?
Even if you can't have the berries, so pluck pluck them off,
right, why should fixing it not work? You plucked off the berries.
So here's how the גמרא's Gemara going to explain what that debate
is about. סברוה, savruha, we're assuming דכולי עלמא לולב צריך אגד. d'chulei
alma lulav tzarich eged. Everybody is assuming that you have to make
a knot in your סוכה. Sukkah. We'll see later it's a debate
whether a לולב lulav you have to knot the three together like
we do, the לולב, lulav, the הדס, hadas, and the ערבה. arava.
We do it with this accordion type of a thing. I actually
don't like the accordion thing, I actually just take a string, a
strand of the לולב lulav leaf and I sort of make it
thin, I you know do it lengthwise and I use it as
a nice string and I make a double knot. We can talk
about that when we get to the third פרק. perek. But anyway,
that's the idea that you have to knot the three things together.
So that's a position of רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, but now we're
going to assume that everybody holds with that position. If that's true,
right, otherwise what's the תעשה ta'aseh for the לולב, lulav, for the
you know, for the המינים? ha-minim? You're not making them. making it
into the מצוה Mitzvah object, what, plucking it off the tree? And
anyway, why don't we say the plucking of the berries is the
making of it? So the only way you have a תעשה Ta'aseh
problem by לולב Lulav is if you have to make it into
a bundle. If there's an idea of a bundle of three of
them, and that's made by knotting them together, that's the making. Now
we can get an interesting scenario. You bundle them together and you
knotted them together, and one of them was invalid. So that's like
putting the סכך Sechach on the top of the סוכה Sukkah while
it's invalid. Now you're going to make it valid, you're going to
pluck the berries off. So now you've made it כשר, Kosher, but
after it's already been physically made into that object, after it's been
made into the bundle, now you're making it כשר. Kosher. So maybe,
says the גמרא, Gemara, that's the debate that's going on here, whether
the plucking of the berries once it's in the bundle can be
considered like you've now made the bundle, whether you've done the right
making of the לולב Lulav or not. So let's take a look.
Okay, so it says like this.
Okay.
סברו דכולי עלמא לולב צריך אגד, Savru de-kulei alma lulav tzarich egged,
you need to make it into a bundle, so therefore there's an
idea of making it. וילפינן לולב מסוכה Ve-yalfinan lulav mi-sukkah and we
learn לולב Lulav from סוכה Sukkah that there's an act of making.
דכתיב גבי סוכה תעשה, De-ketiv gabei sukkah ta'aseh, you
shall
make, where the rabbinic interpretation is ולא מן העשוי, Ve-lo min he-asui,
not something that is sort of made by itself. So and the
same way if you need a bundle by a לולב, Lulav, you
have an act of, you need to do an act of making.
ומאי לאו בהא קמיפלגי, U-mai lav be-haka kamipalgi, let's see if this
is what they debate. דמאן דמכשיר סבר, De-man de-machshir savar, the one
that says it's כשר Kosher holds, אמרינן גבי סוכה קציצתן זו היא
עשייתן, Aminein gabei sukkah ketizatan zu hi asiyatan,
that the cutting of it is the making of it and you
would say that by the סכך Sechach of the סוכה. Sukkah. וגבי
לולב נמי אמרינן לקיטתן זו היא עשייתן, Ve-gabei lulav nami aminein lekitatan
zu hi asiyatan, similar by plucking the berries. When you pluck the
berries and made it into a כשר הדס, Kosher hadas, now that
is considered the act of making it into a bundle. ומאן דפסול,
Ve-man de-pasul, the one that says it's invalid, סבר לא אמרינן גבי
סוכה קציצתן זו היא עשייתן. Savar lo aminein gabei sukkah ketizatan zu
hi asiyatan. No, cutting is not an act of making, it doesn't
work by סוכה. Sukkah. וגבי לולב נמי לא אמרינן לקיטתן זו היא
עשייתן Ve-gabei lulav nami lo aminein lekitatan zu hi asiyatan and similar
by לולב Lulav we don't say plucking the berries makes it into,
is the act of making and therefore it remains invalid because it
was already part of the bundle. So maybe that's the exact debate
whether the, the cutting and the making of it כשר Kosher is
like the act of making of the object. So, so is that
a way to read it? גמרא Gemara says לא, Lo, not necessarily,
a lot of other ways they could be debating. I'll give you
this possible possibility. דכולי עלמא לא אמרינן גבי סוכה קציצתן זו היא
עשייתן. De-kulei alma lo aminein gabei sukkah ketizatan zu hi asiyatan. Everybody
holds like שמואל, Shmuel, which is clearly the direction the גמרא Gemara
is going, that cutting does not make it, is not considered an
act of making. והכא בילוף לולב מסוכה קמיפלגי. Ve-hacha be-illuf lulav mi-sukkah
kamipalgi. And maybe I'll even concede that you need to have an
אגד Egged by a סוכה Sukkah by a לולב. Lulav. But that
doesn't mean that the word, when do we say this principle of
תעשה ולא מן העשוי? Ta'aseh ve-lo min he-asui? It's not a universal
principle. Anytime you need a מצוה Mitzvah object you have to actively
make it. We limit it to places where the verse says תעשה.
Ta'aseh. גדילים תעשה לך Gedilim ta'aseh lecha like ציצית, Tzitzit, you shall
make for yourself ציצית. Tzitzit. חג הסכות תעשה לך, Chag ha-sukkot ta'aseh
lecha, you shall make. So it's like, you know what, maybe לולב
Lulav need have to be a bundle, but nobody ever told you
you needed an active act of making. It never says תעשה Ta'aseh
by לולב. Lulav. Okay, so that's the debate. Do you learn לולב
Lulav from סוכה? Sukkah? מאן דמכשיר סבר לא ילפינן לולב מסוכה, Man
de-machshir savar lo yalfinan lulav mi-sukkah, the one that says it's כשר
Kosher says you don't learn לולב Lulav from סוכה, Sukkah, סוכה Sukkah
might have to be a bundle, but it doesn't need an active
act of making. ומאן דפסול, Ve-man de-pasul, the one that says it's
invalid, סבר ילפינן לולב מסוכה. Savar yalfinan lulav mi-sukkah. No, the same
way סוכה Sukkah needs an active act of making, the same is
true by the לולב. Lulav. That's one way they could debate. They
all agree you need a bundle, they all agree cutting isn't good.
The question is do you need an active act of making? Do
you need תעשה? Ta'aseh? ואיבעית אימא, Ve-iba'it eima, here's another way of
saying the debate. אי סבירא לן דלולב צריך אגד, I sevira lan
de-lulav tzarich egged, were we to hold that you needed a bundle
and, you know, by לולב, Lulav, כולי עלמא לא פליגי דילפינן לולב
מסוכה. Kulei alma lo paligi de-yalfinan lulav mi-sukkah. Everybody would concede you
need a bundle by לולב, Lulav, so we're going to learn it
from סוכה, Sukkah, you need to actively make the bundle. והכא בהא
קמיפלגי, Ve-hacha be-haka kamipalgi, this will be the debate. מר סבר צריך
אגד, Mar savar tzarich egged, one holds it needs to be a
bundle and therefore plucking the berries afterwards is no good because when
it was made into a bundle it was invalid. ומר סבר אין
צריך אגד, Ve-mar savar ein tzarich egged, and the other says it
doesn't need to be a bundle, and therefore what do I care
if you pluck the berries after? Okay, it doesn't have to be
a bundle to begin with, so there's no problem of indirectly making
it. Nothing has to be made, you don't need a bundle. ובפלוגתא
דהני תנאי, U-be-plugta de-hanei tannai, and this question whether לולב Lulav needs
a bundle or not, so we're basically now by the way done
with the discussion of תעשה ולא מן העשוי. Ta'aseh ve-lo min he-asui.
We've agreed that, we've shown that all the weight, although רב Rav
is the simple sense of the משנה, Mishnah, the weight of the
גמרא's Gemara discussion and the weight of the ברייתא Baraita points to
שמואל, Shmuel, that once something is made, cutting it and making it
כשר Kosher is not an act of making. Okay. And, and therefore,
and what's going on by לולב Lulav is different discussions whether it
needs an אגד, Egged, doesn't it need an אגד Egged and so
on, whether לולב Lulav Requires an act of making, but the general
principle is if something needs to be made, like ציצית tzitzit or
לולב, lulav, or סוכה, sukkah, it has to be made when the
thing is כשר, kosher, you can't make it and then even by
doing the physical act like cutting it, that would not, that would
not be enough to be considered that you have made it. Okay?
So, Dov does raise, or I should just repeat, an interesting question,
what if you made the סכך schach and afterwards the walls were
made? It had reminded me that there's some ראשונים, Rishonim, פוסקים, poskim,
אחרונים acharonim want to bring a proof to that from a discussion
earlier in the גמרא. Gemara. I remember the גמרא Gemara says like
if something works for שבת, Shabbat, it works for סוכה, sukkah, like
if it was סוכת שבת Sukkat Shabbat and you had the לחי
lechi and it worked for your מבוי mavoi on שבת, Shabbat, now
it's going to work for סוכה. sukkah. So some say, "Ah, look,
that's a case where the walls got made after the סכך schach
was already up because you had the סכך schach up, you had
two walls, came שבת, Shabbat, and then that was like a third
wall got created." So that's an interesting example used for the idea
that maybe making the walls after the סכך schach is כשר. kosher.
But here we're talking about the סכך schach as the focus, and
when the סכך schach is up, it has to be כשר. kosher.
Yes? Yeah, usually we follow רב Rav in disputes with שמואל. Shmuel.
I know, but usually, but here when all the evidence points in
one way and the discussion of the גמרא Gemara points in one
way. So now let's just wrap up this issue of לולב צריך
אגד. Lulav tzarich egged. ופלוגתא דהני תנאי, U'pelugta de'hani tanna'ei, and this
is based on the debate of תנאים. Tannaim. דתניא, De'tanya, we taught
in a ברייתא, Baraita, לולב בין אגוד בין שאינו אגוד כשר, Lulav
bein agud bein she'eino agud kosher, whether a לולב lulav is bound
together with the הדס hadas and the ערבה aravah it's כשר. kosher.
רבי יהודה אומר אגוד כשר שאינו אגוד פסול, Rabbi Yehuda omer agud
kosher she'eino agud pasul, only if it's bound is it כשר. kosher.
מאי טעמא דרבי יהודה, Mai ta'ama de'Rabbi Yehuda, what's his reasoning? יליף
לקיחה לקיחה מאגודת אזוב. Yalif lekichah lekichah me'agudat ezov. He learns the
verse "take, take," it says "take a לולב" lulav and it says
"take the bundle of the אזוב," ezov, and
there the object that's taken is a bundle with the other sort
of things that are mentioned. Here too it has to be bundled.
כתיב התם ולקחתם אגודת אזוב, Ketiv hatam u'lekachtem agudat ezov, you take
a bundle of אזוב, ezov, right, which is bundled with other things,
וכתיב הכא ולקחתם לכם ביום הראשון, u'chetiv hacha u'lekachtem lachem bayom harishon,
מה להלן באגוד אף כאן באגוד, mah lahalan be'agud af kan be'agud,
the same way that's a bundle of the other objects mentioned, here
too. By the way, why not also bundle up the אתרוג? etrog?
If you have to bundle it, why does the אתרוג etrog have
to... so you could just say it's physically a little awkward, but
who cares? If you need a bundle, you need a bundle. So
the גמרא Gemara discusses it later, but I'll just tell you, it's
indicated by the פסוקים, psukim, because it says ולקחתם לכם u'lekachtem lachem
by the פסוק: pasuk: ולקחתם לכם ביום הראשון פרי עץ הדר,
u'lekachtem lachem bayom harishon
pri etz hadar, comma, כפות תמרים, kapot tmarim, וענף עץ עבות, ve'anaf
etz avot, וערבי נחל, ve'arvei nachal, right, ושמחתם. u'semachtem. So there's no
ו vav that connects the אתרוג etrog to the לולב, lulav, but
the לולב lulav has a ו vav connecting the לולב lulav and
the ערבי נחל arvei nachal and the הדס hadas and the ערבי
נחל. arvei nachal. So those are all connected with a ו, vav,
but they're not connected to the אתרוג. etrog. So that actually is
how they learn that the bundle is without the אתרוג. etrog. Okay.
ורבנן, Ve'rabbanan, what do the Rabbis say back? לקיחה מלקיחה לא ילפינן.
Lekichah mi'lekichah lo yalfinan. We don't make that connection. כמאן אזלא הא
דתניא, Keman azla ha de'tanya, who is it going like that which
we teach in a ברייתא? Baraita? לולב מצוה לאגדו, Lulav mitzvah le'agdo,
it's a מצוה mitzvah to make the bundle, ואם לא אגדו כשר,
ve'im lo agdo kosher, and if you didn't make it, it's still
כשר. kosher. אי רבי יהודה, Ei Rabbi Yehuda, if it's רבי יהודה,
Rabbi Yehuda, כי לא אגדו מאי כשר? ki lo agdo mai kosher?
Then why is it כשר? kosher? רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda explicitly says
if it's not in a bundle it's פסול. pasul. אי רבנן, Ei
Rabbanan, if it's the Rabbis, אמאי מצוה? amai mitzvah? Where's this מצוה
mitzvah coming from? לעולם רבנן, Le'olam Rabbanan, it is the Rabbis, ומשום
שנאמר זה קלי ואנוהו, u'mishum shene'emar zeh keili ve'anveihu, it's because of
the idea "this is my God and I will beautify Him" or
glorify Him, התנאה לפניו במצוות, hitna'eh lefanav be'mitzvot, glorify yourself in front
of Him in the doing of מצוות, mitzvot, which is interpreted to
mean make the מצוות mitzvot look beautiful. So bundling it up is
not a requirement of a bundle per se, it is a way
of making it look beautiful. Now I should say, and we'll discuss
it more when we learn the פרק perek שלישי, shelishi, that there's
an interesting debate. Is the idea here purely aesthetic, this idea of
an אגד egged for the Rabbis? So even if it's not halachically,
let's say, a technical knot, you know, but you make a beautiful
thing that brings them all together, but it's not technically like knotted
together, it's all really an aesthetic point? It looks nicer when it's
all together. Or are they saying, no, that almost at like a
conceptual level, making it a bundle is a, you know, having it
halachically be knotted together, you know, is what is considered to be
a nicer fulfillment even beyond the aesthetic point. So this leads to
the issue of like you have to make a double knot. Like
some people, like me personally, I don't like those accordion things, A,
I don't like it because the leaves always get pulled off, and
B, I actually think that the simple string and the knot actually
looks nicer, it looks more, I don't know, it just more natural.
But anyway, I will, it's very trivial, it's so easy. Anyway, but
some people will say actually it's not כשר, kosher, it's not not
כשר, kosher, but you don't fulfill the Rabbinic idea, the Rabbis לכתחילה
lechatchila of אגד egged because it's not a double knot, and for
an אגד egged you need a double knot. So if you say
it's just an issue of aesthetics, who cares if it constitutes a
double knot or not? But if you say no, it's a concept
of being a bundle, of a halachic bundle, then that... Then you
might even for the rabbis to get that לכתחילה *lechatchila* need a
double knot. Others say because it's held very firmly, it serves the
same function as a double knot, but anyway there is an important
question of what does this זה קלי ואנוהו *zeh keli ve'anvehu* mean
in this context, if it's limited just to the aesthetic point. Okay,
we will end with that.